<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ansvver of the Commissioners of the kingdome of Scotland, to both Houses of Parliament, upon the new propositions of peace, and the foure bills to be sent to his Majestie.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E421_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863444</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E421[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ansvver of the Commissioners of the kingdome of Scotland, to both Houses of Parliament, upon the new propositions of peace, and the foure bills to be sent to his Majestie.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Bostock, dwelling at the sign of the Kings head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>B1r has two side-notes. Variant: with one side-note.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "21 Decemb".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115646:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE Kingdome of Scotland, To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, Upon the New Propoſitions of Peace, AND THE Foure <hi>Bills</hi> to be ſent to his MAJESTIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for ROBERT BOSTOCK, dwelling at the ſign of the Kings head in PAULS Church-yard. 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115646:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115646:2"/>
            <head>The Anſwer of the Commiſsioners of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland</hi> to both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="answer">
               <p>WE have, with much patience, for divers years together, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the Solemn League and Covenant, and Treaties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kingdoms, uſed our beſt indevors for ſetling Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and a happy Peace. Propoſitions were firſt agreed an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Anno</hi> 1644. with advice and conſent of the Parliaments of both Kingdoms, preſented to his Majeſty at <hi>Oxford</hi> by Commiſſioners of both, and treated upon at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1645. We did earneſtly and frequently preſs the ſending of thoſe Propoſitions again to his Majeſty, wherein the Houſes would not concur with us; but on the contrary (after very long delay) thought fit to make ſeveral alterations therein, which were principally in matters that did concern the neer Union of the Kingdoms. Yet were we ſo earneſtly deſirous of putting an end to the long continued diſtraction and troubles of theſe Kingdoms, as (waving what might be conceived to be for the particular intereſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi>) we did joyn with the Houſes of Parliament in preſenting Propoſitions to his Majeſty at <hi>New-caſtle;</hi> though, as we then declared, we had juſt reaſon to be unſatisfied with divers things contained in thoſe Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>When it was agreed upon betwixt the Kingdoms, that the ſame Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould be again preſented to his Majeſty, at his coming to <hi>Holdenby,</hi> the performance thereof being delayed by the Houſes, for divers moneths, we did patiently wait then leaſure. Yet upon the ſudden they did appoint a peremptory day for ſending the Propoſitions to his Majeſty; and gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Commiſſioners, in caſe we were not preciſely upon that day at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> that they ſhould preſent the Propoſitions to the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by themſelves, contrary to the Treaty betwixt the Kingdoms; which was ſo ſtrange and unequal a way, as we might have juſtly denyed our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence, had not our love to Peace prevailed with us to joyn in that Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. but after all this, finding no ſucceſs in that way of ſending Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the King, and inſiſting upon his poſitive Aſſent thereunto, without giving any reaſons for the juſtice of our deſires, or hearing any Propoſition from his Majeſty: We did, in <hi>November</hi> laſt, propoſe to the honorable Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, &amp; with much earne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>neſs deſire, that there might be a perſonal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with his <hi>Majeſty</hi> here at <hi>London,</hi> it being in all probability, the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to obtain a Peace.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115646:3"/>
               <p>About the time of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> withdrawing from <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> the Houſes did communicate to us new Propoſitions, reſolved on by them to be preſented to his <hi>Majeſty;</hi> after receipt whereof, we did in our Paper of the 17. of <hi>November,</hi> inſiſt on our former deſire for a perſonal Treaty with his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> But receiving no Anſwer to that, nor to our paper of the 5. And our poſitive Anſwer being demanded to the new Propoſitions; upon the 23. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> we reſolved once again to deſire an Anſwer to our former Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; A perſonal Treaty being, in our judgment, a readier way to compoſe all differences, then the ſending of theſe new Propoſitions, wherein there are ſo great and eſſential differences from what was formerly agreed on by both Kingdoms. And to the end there might be no let or delay on our part, which might hinder the ſetling of a Peace; We deſired a conference with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of both Houſes concerning the expediency of a perſonal Treaty with his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and the alterations made in the Propoſitions, that ſo according to the Treaty of the 29. of <hi>Novem.</hi> 1643. there might be, with the advice and conſent of both Nations, a ſpeedy Agreement in thoſe things, which are to be the foundation of the Peace of both. To all which, the Houſes have been pleaſed to return no Anſwer. However, it is no ſmal ſatisfaction to us, that we leave no means of Agreement uneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayed; and that the retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſetling of the Peace of the Kingdoms, cannot be charged on us. And leaſt our further ſilence, in expectation of an Anſwer, ſhould be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, We have thought fit to repreſent our ſence, concerning a perſonal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Propoſitions, to the Houſes in writing; which, had our deſires been granted, we did intend to have done by a verbal conference.</p>
               <p>There be ſome things which properly concern the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> their Rights, Laws, and Liberties. But there be other matters, which in their own nature, as being common to both, or by Covenant, or Treaty, concern both Kingdoms, wherein, unleſs we would forget our duty to God, to the Kings Majeſty, to our Native Kingdom, and to this Nation, Our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concernment and intereſt, cannot be denyd. For as <hi>Scotland</hi> was invited and ingaged in this War, upon grounds &amp; reaſons of common intereſt; So we truſt it wil not be offenſive, that in making of Peace we claim from the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes an Improvement of the very ſame principles, and a performance of the Treaties they have made with us; that the ſame meaſure of conjunction of intereſts be given to us which was had of us, and promiſed unto us; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the very Law of Nations, and the rule of common equity, doth plead for us. Yet in the application of this rule, we ſhal not ſtretch our ſelves beyond our line, the expreſs conditions of our Solemn League and Covenant, the duty of our Allegiance, and the Treaties and Declarations between the Kingdoms, which are ſo many ſtrong obligations, as, all who have honor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115646:3"/> or conſcience, muſt acknowledg ſhould be inviolably obſerved.</p>
               <p>Having layd this as a moſt juſt and ſolid ground of our proceedings, we ſhal firſt ſpeak of the beſt and moſt probable means to procure a good A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the King for ſetling Religion and a laſting Peace: And next of the Propoſitions, which are to be the foundation of the peace and ſafety of both Kingdoms. And it is ſtil our Opinion and Judgment, that the moſt equal, faireſt, and juſt way to obtain a wel-grounded peace, is by a perſonal Treaty with the King: and that his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> for that end, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to come to <hi>London,</hi> with Honor, Freedom, and Safety: For which we offer the Reaſons following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſending of Propoſitions, without a Treaty, hath been often eſſayed without ſucceſs: And the new Propoſitions are leſs to the advantage of the Crown than the former. Therefore, we have no reaſon to expect better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction that way than formerly we had.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Kings removall from his Parliament, is acknowledged by the Houſes in ſeverall Declarations, to be the chiefe cauſe of all the War, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and calamities of the Kingdomes. Then, his Majeſties preſence with his Parliament muſt be the beſt, if not the onely remedy, to remove our troubles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In a perſonall Treaty the Commiſſioners of both Kingdomes, may give reaſons for the equity and expediencie of our deſires. But without a Treaty or giving reaſons for aſſerting the lawfulneſs and expediency of the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to be preſented, they may be eſteemed Impoſitions.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The King may have ſome juſt deſires to move for the Crown, and for himſelf: As that he may have his Revenues, and that he may be reſtored to his Royal Government: which may be done, with greater honor and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to him, by a perſonal Treaty, then otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A perſonal Treaty with the King is the beſt way to beget a mutual confidence between Him and his Parliament: It is the beſt way to cleer his doubts and to remove all difficulties: and it is the abſolute beſt way for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and receiving mutual ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p n="6">6. We cannot expect that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> wil grant <hi>in terminis</hi> whatſoever Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions ſhal be ſent unto him: nor can every thing in the Propoſitions be of that importance, as that the not granting of it ought to hinder a Peace. Neither wil the <hi>Houſes of Parliament</hi> give ful power to their Commiſſioners to make alterations in the Propoſitions, as they ſhal ſee cauſe upon debate. Wherefore, a perſonal Treaty with his <hi>Majeſty</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> is the moſt probable and expeditious way to remove or reconcile all differences.</p>
               <p>There is one common obiection, wherewith many are poſſeſſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced againſt a perſonal Treaty with the King, and his coming to <hi>London,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115646:4"/>
[That his preſence may breed diviſion, and continue our troubles: And that when his Majeſty deſired to come hither from Oxford with freedome and ſafety, it was thought unfit, and denyed by the Houſes, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners from Scotland]</hi> But that argument now hath no force at all: For the caſe of affairs, the Kings condition and ours (which were given for Reaſons in that Anſwer to his Majeſty) are quite altered from what they were then. Then the King had Armies in the fields; he had Garriſons and ſtrong holds to return to; Now, he hath none of theſe. And his Maieſty offers a ful ſecurity againſt all hoſtility or danger can be expected from him, by granting to the Houſes the power of the Militia by Sea and Land, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Raign, as is expreſſed in his Maieſties late Meſſage from <hi>Caresbrook Castle.</hi> And for a further anſwer, we deſire the Houſes to remember that Reply to his Maieſties Meſſage of the 11 of <hi>September,</hi> 1642. Where, after mention of their chief grievances, they ſay <hi>[All this notwithſtanding, as we never gave your Majeſtie any juſt cauſe of withdrawing your ſelf from your great Councell: So it hath ever bin, and ſhal be far from as, to give any impediment to your return: Or to neglect any proper means of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the diſtempers of the Kingdom, and cloſing the dangerous breaches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your Majeſty and your Parliament, according to the great trust which lyeth upon us. And if your Majeſty ſhal now be pleaſed to come back to your Parliament without your Forces: We ſhal be ready to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your Royal Perſon, Crown and Dignity, with our lives and fortunes, Your preſence in this great Councel, being the only means of any Treaty betwixt your Majeſty and them, with hope of ſucceſs.]</hi> And if they were eſteemed Enemies to the Parliament, and the Peace of the Kingdoms, who adviſed the King to withdraw from his Parliament: What eſtimation wil the world have of them, who after ſuch a Declaration, wil not ſuffer him to return to his Parliament, when he offers to caſt himſelf into their Arms? If ſo kind an offer ſhal be refuſed, and the King driven to deſpair, it is to be feared, theſe Kingdoms ſhal be involved into greater difficulties then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And therefore we do hold, that the admitting the King to come to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don with Honor, Freedom and Safety, and granting of a perſonal Treaty with his Maieſty, upon ſuch Propoſitions as ſhal be agreed upon by advice and conſent of both Kingdoms, is the moſt probable, and only beſt means, with hope of ſucceſs, for ſetling a wel-grounded Peace.</p>
               <p>Having ſpoken of the readi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t means to obtain a juſt and laſting peace; We ſhal next fall upon the Conſideration of the Propoſitions, which are to be the Foundation of our peace. And the moſt compendious and ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t way to a good agreement, and unanimous Reſolution upon them, is, in the firſt place to conſider and remove our differences, which are chiefly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115646:4"/> Religion, the Intereſt of the Crown, and in the Union and Joynt Conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>We ſhall begin with that of Religion, which for the incomparable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence thereof (although it be amongſt the laſt of theſe new Propoſitions) deſerves the preference. It is the <hi>primum quarite,</hi> the <hi>unum neceſſarium;</hi> We ought to build the Houſe of God before our own. The Law of piety and true policy doth require that Religion, which rendreth to God his due, have the precedency. And therefore (upon debate) before we went to the Treaty at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg,</hi> it was agreed betwixt the houſes and us, that the Propoſitions of Religion ſhould be in the firſt place, and firſt Treated and Agreed upon, before any Agreement upon any other Propoſition. And his Maieſty in his late Meſſage from <hi>Careſbrook Castle,</hi> begins at Religion, as the beſt and chiefeſt Foundation for Peace. Wherefore, if this changing of the former Order and Method of the Propoſitions, be only their Error, to whom the reviewing of the Propoſitions was committed. And if the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have not faln away from their firſt Zeal. We deſire that it may be recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the former Method keeped. And ſo we come to the matter of the Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>The material differences and alterations concerning Religion, may be branched into the Errour of Omiſſion and Deficiency, and into that of Commiſſion and Exceſs. That which is left out, is no leſs then the Solemn League and Covenant. And ſhal the Covenant, which is as Solemn a vow, as Creatures on Earth could make to God in Heaven, and the greateſt tye betwixt men on Earth (to which the moſt high and dreadful Name of the Lord God Almighty, was interpoſed) be offered up in a Sacrifice, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed in the aſhes of Oblivion? Shal our Covenant for the Preſervation and Reformation of Religion, for the honor and happyneſs of the King, and the peace and ſafety of the three Kingdoms; and for the maintenance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Laws, and true publick Liberties of theſe Kingdoms; which was declared by both Kingdoms, to be a fit and moſt Excellent means to acquire the favour of God towards both, and likewiſe to Unite them, and by uniting, to ſtrengthen them againſt the common Enemies of the true Reformed Religion, and the Peace and Proſperity of theſe Kingdoms; and which in all former Propoſitions was deſired to be eſtabliſhed: be now d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, as unworthy to take room amongſt theſe new Propoſitions? Shal the Covenant, which both Houſes did recommend to the Aſſembly of Divines, to make a Declaration to all ſorts of perſons to take it, as that which they judged not only Lawful, but exceeding expedient and neceſſary for all that wiſh wel to Religion, the King and Kingdom to ioyn in, and to be a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar pledg of Gods gracious goodneſs to all the three Kingdoms (we ſay) ſhal that Covenant be layd aſide? Shal our mutual and ſolemn League and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115646:5"/> Covenant ſubſcribed by the Parliaments of both Kingdoms, by the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines, by the City of London, and which, not only they, but all Scotland, and many thouſands in England and Ireland, with hands lifted up to the moſt high God, did ſwear <hi>[That they ſhal not ſuffer themſelves directly or indirectly by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion or terror, to be divided and withdrawn from that bleſſed union and conjunction, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make defection to the contrary part, or to give themſelves to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable indifferency or neutrality in this cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms, and honor of the King: but ſhal all the days of their lives, zealouſly and constantly continue therein againſt all oppoſition: and promote the ſame according to their power, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all lets and impediments whatſoever: and that they ſhal do all this as in the ſight of God]</hi> Shal that Covenant (even with thoſe that took it) be already out of date, and not ſo much as remembred amongſt the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons of Peace? Yea, it is not ſo much as mentioned in theſe new Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, except in the 7 Qualification of the 14 Propoſition, where it is only made a hook to catch ſome into the Notion of Delinquency! But perhaps there it eſcaped the Reviſers of the Propoſitions, who in all other places have exploded it.</p>
               <p>It is anſwered by ſome, that by one of the Propoſitions it is craved, that an act of Parliament be paſſed, declaring the Kings approbation of the making of the Treaties between the Kingdoms of Scotland and England; in which Treaties there is mention made of the Covenant: And therefore it is not neceſſary to deſire a particular Confirmation and Eſtabliſhment of the Covenant. To which it is briefly Replyed, firſt, that there is no Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for paſſing any Act of Parliament, to confirm the Treaties between the Kingdoms, as was deſired in all former Propoſitions; but theſe words are purpoſely changed, and in place thereof there is only deſired, An Act De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the Kings approbation of the making of the Treaties; which in effect is no more then an act of Indempnity for making the Treaties, and not an Act for confirmation and eſtabliſhing of the Treaties themſelves, and thoſe things which are expreſſed and tranſacted in them. 2. Suppoſe there were an Act of Parliament paſſed for approbation of the Treaties between the Kingdoms in general (which is not in theſe Propoſitions) Yet ſuch a generality would not be underſtood to be extended to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Covenant, unleſs the particular Articles of the Treaty and the Covenant, were expreſly inſerted; becauſe, there was an expreſs Propoſition amongſt the former, that an Act of Parliament be paſſed in both Kingdoms for confirming and taking the Covenant; which being now left out of the new Propoſitions, without mentioning the Covenant cannot but he interpreted as a receding from the Covenant: and the approbation
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115646:5"/> and confirmation of the Treaties in generall (after deleting the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant out of the Propoſitions) would only be underſtood of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Articles of the Treaties. Therefore, if there be not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to relinquiſh the Covenant; Let us not be aſhamed to avow it and inſert the confirming of it, as one of the chiefe and expreſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of our Propoſitions: <hi>[Let us give teſtimony, and beare witneſſe to the truth and not deny it, remembring that whoſoever ſhall give teſtimony to Chriſt and his truth by confeſſing him before Men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.33</note> 
                  <hi>he will alſo confeſſe them before his Father which is in heaven: And whoſoever will deny him before Men, them will he deny before his Father which is in heaven.]</hi> And ſeeing the Covenant was the ſoverain and only meanes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering theſe embroiled bleeding Kingdomes, when the Houſes were at their loweſt ebbe, and deſired the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Declarat. deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Iuly 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>[to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with what difficulties, miſeries, and diſtractions, they were enforced daily to wreſtle, even for the life and being both of Church and State:]</hi> Surely, the deſpiſing, refuſing, and caſting aſide that remedy, would be the height of ingratitude, muſt render the diſeaſe much more deſperate, and turn our former mutuall confidence into mutuall diffidence. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deſire, that the Houſes upon better conſideration, will ſtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Covenant, and inſert it among the Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>And whereas the Kings averſneſſe from the Covenant may be obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and that the deſiring to have it confirmed, may be a hinderance to peace: We anſwer, If the omitting of the Covenant in theſe Propoſitions doth really proceed from that principle, that the Houſes are deſirous to pleaſe the King, and to remove all obſtructions that may hinder a peace: We doe very much wonder, that they are ſo liberall in the matters of God, and ſo tenacious in what concernes themſelves, in all differences betwixt his Majeſty and them in things Civill, which may farre better be diſpenced with. But to anſwer the ſtrength of the Objection, We ſay, That the Covenant being for the preſervation and Reformation of Religion, and for the true honour and happineſſe of the King and his Poſterity, and for the peace and ſafety of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; Whatever be the difference of his Majeſties judgement, We have juſt cauſe to inſiſt to crave his Royall aſſent to it; And the Kings heart is in the hands of God, to turn it as the rivers of waters whither he pleaſeth: And although the King ſhould deny it, yet we ought to performe our duty: And when his Majeſty ſhall be convinced, that our intentions in entring into this Covenant, were and are pious and loyall; and that our Actions doe evidence that we intend no injury to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115646:6"/> his Royall Perſon, to wrong his Government, nor to diminiſh his juſt power: We hope God will incline his heart to give juſt ſatisfaction concerning the Covenant. And though his Majeſty ſhall not come the full length of our deſires, yet we muſt never depart from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, nor leave off by all juſt wayes to promote it, or deſiſt from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring by all lawfull meanes to procure his Majeſties aſſent unto it. But we deſire that we may be rightly underſtood in this, and not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrued; as if our zeale for the Covenant did abate or diminiſh at all from our Loyalty and duty to the King, (for the Covenant doth not leſſen or limit our allegeance, as ſome would falſely ſlander it, and thoſe who ſincerely and loyally took it) or that upon difference of his Majeſties judgement, and not comming the full length of our deſires in every thing, he ſhould be kept in priſon; or that Armes ſhould be kept up (now when the Warre is ended) to burthen the Subjects, and force the King to grant what they pleaſe to demand. We were confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (when our Army returned to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and left no Forces in this Kingdome to oppoſe the Parliament) that the Army here ſhould have been inſtantly disbanded: And could never have expected that the Kings Majeſty, to whom the Parliaments of both Kingdomes were to make their addreſſes for a ſafe and well-grounded peace, ſhould have been taken away by the Army againſt his will, and ſtill kept in their power, to be carryed whether they pleaſe, or forced to flye for ſafety. If <hi>Scotland</hi> had apprehended, that the leaſt injury or violence would have been committed againſt his Majeſties Royall Perſon, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall Government: Nay, if they had not received aſſurance from the Houſes to the contrary, certainly all the threatnings or allurements in the world, could never have perſwaded them to have parted with the King till all Armies had been disbanded and the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſetled It was our brotherly confidence in the Houſes (who are our fellow Subjects) and the aſſurance we had from them that made us leave the King with them: And their care of him and duty to him ought to be ſuch, as neither his Majeſty, nor we, have cauſe to repent it. And this we could not but declare to aſſert the truth, and vindicate the honour and reputation of our Nation; for out Loyalty hath ever been, is and ſhall be dearer unto us, then our lives and fortunes; And the candor and integrity of all our Actions, is a ſufficient confutation of all the calumnyes and aſperſions, which malice or envie can forge againſt us.</p>
               <p>We finde alſo theſe Propoſitions omitted, <hi>viz.</hi> the Propoſition for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115646:6"/> confirming the Ordinances concerning the calling and ſitting of the Aſſembly of Divines; the Propoſition for Reformation of Religion in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the Covenant; And the Propoſition for ſetling Unity and Uniformity in matters of Religion between the Churches of God in both Kingdomes, according to the Covenant. In place of all which we finde nothing but a meer ſhadow of <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Government, an externall Form of Diſcipline without life or power; and a liberty granted for all ſorts of Service and Worſhip of God, and for the Exerciſe of all ſuch Religious Duties and Ordinances as every perſon ſhall pleaſe, and his own erroneous conſcience ſhall dictate unto him (for there is no other rule preſcribed) which opens a doore to Atheiſm to all Religions, and to that which (by abuſe of the name) is called liberty of conſcience; being indeed liberty of errour, ſcandall, ſchiſm, hereſy, diſhonouring God, oppoſing the truth, hindering Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and ſeducing others; So, in place of Uniformity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which by Covenant both Kingdomes have ſworn to endeavour, there is here deſired to be ſetled a vaſt difformity or multi-formity of Hereſies and Sects; which, if the Lord in his mercy ſhall not prevent, may produce the ruine of Religion in both Kingdomes, which we have juſt reaſon to feare; as for other reaſons, ſo when we conſider the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Houſes of Parliament, ſpeaking of the deſign of the Popiſh and Prelaticall Faction to alter Religion in this Iſland: of whom they ſay, firſt,<note place="margin">Page 492. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar.</note> [<hi>they reſolved to impoſe a Popiſh Service-Book upon</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>for well they know the ſame fate attended both Kingdoms, and Religion could not be altered in the one without the other.</hi>] And in Anſwer to the <hi>Scots</hi> Declaration, pag. 601. <hi>[Whenſoever the deſign to root out Religion ſhall be perfected in either Nation, it will eaſily be accompliſhed in the other, Religion being the band and foundation of the ſafety and happineſſe of both.]</hi> And in Auguſt 1643. the Engliſh Commiſſioners declare to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland, [that they are commanded by their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to put their brethren of</hi> Scotland <hi>in minde, that the Popiſh and Prelaticall Faction, that began with them about the yeare</hi> 1638 <hi>and</hi> 1639, <hi>and then intended to make way to the ruine of the Kingdome of</hi> England <hi>by theirs have not abated any part of their malice toward the Nation and Church of</hi> Scotland; <hi>nor at all departed from their deſign of corrupting and altering Religion through the whole Iſland, though they have inverted the manner of their proceeding, conceiving now that they have an eaſier way to deſtroy them, if they may firſt prevaile over the Parliament and Kingdome of</hi> England; <hi>In which respect it is the deſire
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115646:7"/> of both Houſes, that the two Nations may be ſtrictly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited, &amp;c.]</hi> And in another paper it is declared, that [<hi>what corruptions take root in the Church and Kingdome of</hi> England,<note place="margin">Engliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3,</note> 
                  <hi>will quickly ſpread their venome and infection into the Neighbour Church of</hi> Scotland:] Wherefore, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſſent from this Propoſition; And according to the truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in us, repreſent our juſt exceptions againſt it. And firſt of all we think it very ſtrange, That the Houſes of Parliament ſhould deſire an Act of Parliament to bee made for eſtabliſhing <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and in the very ſame Propoſition, deſire that it may bee Enacted that none ſhall obey that Act of Parliament, but ſuch as ſhall pleaſe to doe it. 2. We obſerve, that however it is pretended that <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government is deſired to be eſtabliſhed, as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> yet it is only in effect, a Liberty granted to all ſuch, as of their own accord will joyn in <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Government, and ſo amounts to no more then a Toleration of it. 3. That this toleration of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government is many wayes limited; as in the time for which it is to endure, being only to the end of the next Seſſion of Parliament, after the end of this preſent Seſſion, which perhaps may be not above ſix Moneths. And the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Elders are appointed by Ordinance of Parliament to exclude from the Sacrament, only ſuch Perſons as the Houſes have thought fit, and no others, though it be againſt their conſciences ſo to do. They are bounded with ſeverall reſtrictions in their Meetings and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyes, and are not allowed the uſe and exerciſe of all the Ordinances appointed by the Word of God; ſo as Liberty of Conſcience is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to them, and granted to others: For, 4. An unlimited tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the time of endurance, matter of worſhip, and exerciſe of all Ordinances, is expreſly granted to all the Sectaries of the time, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be Anabaptiſts, Antinomians, Arminians, Familiſts, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtians, Browniſts, Separatiſts, Libertines, or Independents; yea, it extends to thoſe Nullifidians, the Seekers, to the new Sect of Shakers, and divers others; By all which the very foundation of Church and State is ſhaken, and neare to be overthrown, 5. The toleration here deſired to be eſtabliſhed is of that capacity and latitude, as it may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of many vile and groſſe errours which have been condemned and caſt out of the Church in former times, and may be revived in <hi>England;</hi> as if errours and hereſies were of ſo precious a nature, that men ſhould be encouraged by Law to enquire after them, and invited to maintaine them. 6. This toleration is not only to the perſons of thoſe Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115646:7"/> and their families, but gives a full liberty to ſet up their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in any fit and convenient places, that ſo Scandals, Hereſies, Schiſmes, and new Religions may grow in their kinds, and alſo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply in the number of Profeſſours and Diſciples, as if there were not enough already. 7. Though it ſeemeth that a proviſion is made that this indulgence ſhall not extend to the toleration of Antitrinitarians, Arrians, and Antiſcripturiſts, yet there is no more expreſſed, but that this indulgence ſhall not extend to tolerate the Printing, Publiſhing, or Preaching ſuch blaſphemies and errours as they do maintain againſt God, the Holy Trinity, and the Scriptures. They are not made lyable to any penalty; and ſuppoſe penalties were impoſed upon them for Printing, Publiſhing, or Preaching thoſe errours; yet they are by this Propoſition left to a full liberty to maintain them in private, to reaſon and diſpute that there is no God, that Chriſt is but an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor, that there is no ſuch thing as the Holy Ghoſt, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are but like other writings; blaſpheming at their pleaſure, and ſeducing others to their opinions in ſecret; All which, and much more, according to this Propoſition, may not be queſtioned: and ſo in reality, though not in pretext, they ſhall be tolerated as well as others. 8. Al protane and wicked perſons are left at liberty by this toleration to doe what they pleaſe. For they are not obliged to be ſubject to any Diſcipline or Government, and ſo neither the duties of the firſt nor ſecond table of the Law of God, ſhall be obſerved; but all ſort of impiety and works of darkneſſe, ſhall abound: and ſuch as hate the ſincere worſhip of God in the Church, may have the moſt unlawfull and wicked meetings elſewhere, under a profeſſion of religious exerciſes or Ordinances. We might adde more exceptions againſt this Propoſition; But theſe we truſt may ſuffice to make any that is but a little indued with the light of the Goſpell, and hath any love to the truth, for to deteſt and abhorre ſuch a toleration. And now we deſire the Houſes of Parliament to remember their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the State of the Kingdome of the 15 of December 1642. where they reſent it as a great injury, that any <hi>[ſhould infuſe into the people that they meane to leave every man to his own judgement and fancy for the ſervice and worſhip of God; and do declare, that it is farre from their purpoſe and deſire, to let looſe the golden reynes of Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church, to leave private perſons or particular Congregations, to take up what kinde of divine ſervice they pleaſe; and hold it requiſite,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115646:8"/> that there ſhould be throughout the whole Realme a conformity to that Order, which the Laws enjoyne, according to the word of God.]</hi> How conſonant this toleration is to that Declaration, we leave it to the Houſes of Parliament and all wiſe men to conſider; and whether the danger of the true reformed Religion in theſe Kingdomes, be not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter now then before the taking of the Covenant; yea, or ſince Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion came firſt into this Iſland, when toleration of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (the name of Popery only excepted) is deſired by the Houſes of Parliament to be eſtabliſhed by Law; and the very Principles and Fundamentals of faith, which under Prelacy yea under Popery it ſelfe, were generally received as uncontroverted, are now by many Sectaries of this time, either oppugned or called in queſtion.</p>
               <p>There are divers other paſſages in the Declarations and Ordinances of both Houſes to the ſame purpoſe; but here we ſhall only mention one or two. In particular we would have the Houſes call to minde their Declaration and anſwer to the Lords of his Majeſties Secret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Scotland, and the generall Aſſembly of the Church of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the yeare 1642. where beſides other expreſſions they uſe theſe words <hi>[We acknowledge it an act of love to us, and Wiſdome for the good of both Churches, for which we are thankefull both to God and them, that our Brethren of Scotland have beſtowed their ſerious thoughts and earneſt deſires for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Religion, that in all his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions there might be one confeſſion of faith, one Directory for worſhip, one publick Catechiſme, and one forme of Church Government. And although it will hardly be obtained punctually and exactly, unleſſe ſome way might be found, for a mutuall communication and conjunction of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and debate in frameing that one forme; yet both intending the ſame and, proceeding by the ſame rule of Gods word, and guided by the ſame Spirit: we hope by Gods aſſiſtance to be ſo directed, that we may caſt out whatſoever is offenſive to God or juſtly diſpleaſing to any neighbour Church; And ſo farre agree with our Brethren of Scotland and other reformed Churches in all ſubſtantiall parts of Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, that both we and they may enjoy thoſe advantages and conveniences, which are mentioned by them in this their anſwer; In the more strict <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of both Kingdomes; more ſafe, eaſy, and comfortable Government of his Majesty, and both to himſelfe and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, more free communion in all holy exerciſes and dutyes of worſhip; more conſtant ſecurity of Religion againſt the bloody practiſes of Papiſts, and deceitfull errours of other Sectaries.]</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115646:8"/> And having there made known their reſolution to take away the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Biſhops, they deſire ſome godly and learned Divines of that Church, to bee ſent to the Aſſembly of Divines here, whereby an uniformity in form of Church Government may bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned; and one Confeſſion of Faith, one Directory, and one Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm may be ſetled in all the three Kingdomes: Which deſire was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards renewed to their Commiſſioners ſent to Scotland; and in end the mutuall and joynt deſires of both Kingdomes, were crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a ſolemne League and Covenant; as for other ends, ſo for endeavouring the neareſt conjunction and uniformity in al theſe; and for extirpation of Hereſy and Schiſme. Theſe foure yeares paſt, the labours of many learned and godly Divines of both Kingdomes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appointed, have been ſpent in framing a Directory for worſhip (which was long ſince approved, and received in both Kingdomes,) a Confeſſion of Faith, a form of Church Government and Catechiſing; all which have been preſented to both Houſes, and ſome progreſſe was made therein toward the eſtabliſhing of them, till of late they were laid aſide.</p>
               <p>The Houſes not many months ſince, did appoint a ſolemn Faſt, and day of Humiliation, to be kept throughout the whole kingdome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the growth of Hereſies, Blaſphemies, and Schiſm: The words of the Ordinance are theſe [<hi>We the Lords and Commons aſſembled in the Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>having entred into a ſolemn Covenant, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour ſincerely, really, and conſtantly the reformation of Religion in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip; And the extirpation of Popery, ſuperſtation, hereſie, ſchiſme, prophaneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found contrary to ſound doctrine, and the power of godlineſſe. And having found the preſence of God wonderfully aſſiſting us in this cauſe, eſpecially ſince our ſaid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, in purſuance of the ſaid Covenant, have thought fit (leſt we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in other mens ſins, and therby be in danger to receive of their plagues) to ſet forth this our deep ſence, of the great diſhonour of God, and perillous condition that this Kingdome is in, through the abhominable blaſphemies, and damnable hereſies vented and ſpread abroad therein, tending to the ſubverſion of the faith, contempt of the Miniſtry, and ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt. And as we are reſolved to imploy and improve the utmoſt of our power, that nothing be done or ſaid againſt the truth, but for the truth; So we deſire that both ourſelves and the whole Kingdom may be deeply hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115646:9"/> before the Lord, for that great reproach and contempt, which hath been caſt upon his Name, and ſaving truthes, and for that ſwift deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that we may juſtly fear will fall upon the immortall ſouls of ſuch, who are or may be drawn away by giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits. In the hearty and tender compaſſion whereof, We the ſaid Lords and Commons doe order and ordaine, That Wedneſday being the</hi> 10. <hi>day of</hi> March <hi>next, be ſet apart for a day of publike humiliation, for the growth and ſpreading of errors, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and blaſphemies, to be obſerved in all places within the Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>Dominion of</hi> Wales, <hi>and Town of</hi> Berwick, <hi>and to ſeek God for his direction and aſſiſtance, for the ſuppreſſing and preventing the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And are theſe the waies and meanes that the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have thought upon for ſuppreſsing Errors, Hereſies, and Blaſphemies, to deſire that a Toleration of them may be eſtabliſhed by a Law? Is the laying of a foundation to propagate Hereſie and Schiſme, the beſt way to extirpate the ſame? Are theſe the fruits and effects of their ſolemne Faſt and Humiliation? Certainly God will not be mocked.</p>
               <p>The Covenant doth alſo oblige us, mutually to preſerve the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſupream Magiſtrate, the priviledges of Parliaments, and firm peace and union between the kingdoms to all poſterity. And is it not viſible, that many of thoſe Sectaries, with their adherents and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, doe by their pernicious doctrine and actions, offer violence to the Kings perſon and Authority, and againſt the rights and priviledges of Parliament? So as there is not any one Article of the Solemn League and Covenant, which is not in a high degree violated by them; And ſhall a toleration be eſtabliſhed for all ſuch? The oppoſing the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Reformation of Religion, the dividing betwixt the King and his people, or making any faction among the people, contrary to this League and Covenant, were formerly the characters of our enemies; and whoſoever mayntayn and doe theſe things (though they ſhould aſſume to themſelves the name of Saints) are ſtill to be accounted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries, Malignants, and evill Inſtruments. And we are obliged by Covenant with faithfulneſſe to endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch, that they may bee brought to publique triall, and receive condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115646:9"/>
               <p>And though it be far from our intentions that pious and peaceable men ſhould be troubled, becauſe in every thing they cannot conform themſelves to Presbyteriall Govenment (for we did never oppoſe ſuch an indulgence to their perſons as is agreeable to the Word of God, may ſtand with the publick peace, and is not deſtructive to the order and Government of the Church) yet wee do from our very ſouls abhor ſuch a generall and vaſt Toleration as is expreſſed in the Propoſition. And if the Houſes (which God forbid) ſhall adhere thereunto, and inſiſt that it may be eſtabliſhed, We do proteſt againſt it, as that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contrary to the Word of God, utterly repugnant to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, deſtructive to Reformation and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in Religion, altogether inconſiſtent with the Declarations and Profeſſions of the Houſes, againſt the Treaty between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, directly oppoſite to the example and practice of all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and as that which will unavoidably ſubvert all Order and Goverment, and introduce a world of confuſion. Our mindes are aſtonied, and our bowels are moved within us, when we think of the bitter fruits and ſad conſequences of ſuch a Toleration. What horrid blaſphemies againſt God! What vile abominations! What pernicious doctrine, to the ſubverſion and perdition of ſouls! What diſobedience to the Magiſtrate! What violation of duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween perſons of neereſt relation! What differences and diviſions in Families and Congregations it will bring forth! What bitter heart-burnings it will beget, and perpetuate to poſterity! Nay, it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for us to expreſſe what infinite diſtraction, diſorder, and confuſion it will make both in Church and State thorowout all the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. And therefore wee do obteſt the Houſes of Parliament by the ſolemn League and Covenant (which they have made in the preſence of Almighty God the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intention to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame, as they ſhall anſwer at that great day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed) and by all the promiſes, profeſſions, and Declarations wherewith they induced the Kingdom of Scotland to an engagement and conjunction with them in this Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, That they do not eſtabliſh ſuch an impious Toleration, as cannot but draw down the judgement of God, and make a rent between the two Kingdoms uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſo many tyes and relations, which wee deſire to cheriſh and ſtrengthen, and to continue to all poſterity.</p>
               <p>That next to Religion wherein we differ in judgement from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115646:10"/> Propoſitions, is concerning the intereſt &amp; power of the Crown. We are obliged by our Covenant, allegeance, and the duty of Subjects, not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh but to ſupport the Kings juſt power and greatnes. The queſtion then is, wherein his royall Authority and juſt power doth conſiſt. And we affirm and hope it cannot be denyed, that regall power and authority is chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fly in making and enacting Laws, and in protecting and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſubjects, which are of the very eſſence and being of all Kings. And the exerciſe of that power are the chief parts and duties of their royall office and function; And the Scepter and Sword are the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of that power. Yet the new preface compared with other parts of theſe new Propoſitions, takes away the Kings negative voice, and cuts off all Royall power and righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the making of Laws, contrary to the conſtant practice of this and all other Kingdoms: For the Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative power in ſome Monarchies is <hi>Penes Principem ſolum,</hi> and their Laws are called <hi>Principum placita,</hi> which is the higheſt and moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute kinde of Sovereignty. And in other Kingdoms and Monarchies, the power of making Laws is by compact between the Prince and people, or according to the conſtitution, practice, and uſage of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Kingdoms. In the laſt the power of the King is leaſt; but beſt regulated, where neither the King alone without his Parliament, nor the Parliament without the King can make Laws; and where nothing enacted by the one without the conſent of the other, can have the force of a Law. And although we will rather profeſſe <hi>ignorantiam &amp; facti &amp; juris alieni,</hi> then take upon us to judge of the Laws of another Kingdom; yet it ſeems to be very cleer and evident, by the practice and uſage of all times, by the Parliaments own Declarations, and to be conſonant to reaſon and law, that the King without the Houſes of Parliament, or the Houſes of Parliament without the King, cannot enact any Laws; but both joyntly. And therefore the Lawes are ſometimes called the Kings Laws, ſometimes the Lawes of the Land, and Acts of Parliament. And the form or Acts of Parliament ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times begin with the word <hi>Conciſſinus,</hi> or <hi>Statuit R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x;</hi> And of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times Lawes and Statutes begin, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing enacted by the King with the conſent and advice of the Lord &amp; Commons. All which do in port the Kings power and conſent as to the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Laws<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that there can be no Law made, and have the force of a Law without the King; which likewiſe is cleer by the expreſſions of to Kings anſwers. <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Roy de Vene, &amp; Le Roy S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aviſera;</hi> ſo as it is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t from: the words of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115646:10"/> aſſent, when Statutes are made, and from the words of diſſent, that the Kings power in the making of Laws is one of the chiefeſt jewels of the Crown, and an eſſentiall part of Soveraignty. And if the King had no power nor conſent in making of Laws, he would be leſſe then a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubject. Sometimes the Kings denyall had been better then his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the deſires of the Houſes of Parliament; as when Kings have aſſented to the taking away the reading of Scripture from the Laity, as <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight did; or to introduce Popery, as Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> And ſince neither Kings nor Parliaments have the judgement of infallibility, it muſt certainly be the beſt, where Lawes are made with conſent both of King and Parliament, which is the ſtrongeſt bulwark of the peoples liberty, and ſupporter of the Kings authority. And the King being King over divers Nations, this form of conſtitution where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King without his Parliament, nor the Parliament without the King can make Laws, is a good and ſure ſecurity to preſerve his Kingdomes in peace from injuring one another, and to protect the ſubjects from injury amongſt themſelves. The Houſes of Parliament <hi>pag.</hi> 710 of the Exact collection of Remonſtrances and Declarations, anſwering an argument againſt the Kings paſſing the Bill of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, make this Reply: <hi>If we had ſaid (as wee did not) that the King had been bound to paſſe all Bils that ſhould be offered to him by both Houſes of Parliament, without any limitation or qualification of reaſon or juſtice, yet ſuch a ſuppoſition as this could not fall upon a Parliament, much leſſe that a King were obliged for to grant it.</hi> And page 727, <hi>Wee did and do ſay, that the ſoveraign power doth reſide in the King and both Houſes of Parliament, and that his Majeſties negative voice doth not import a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for his Majeſtie to deny any thing as he pleaſeth, though never ſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and neceſſary for the Kingdom: and yet we did not, nor do ſay, that ſuch Bils as his Majeſtie is bound both in conſcience &amp; juſtice to paſſe, ſhall not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be law without his conſent; ſo far are we from taking away his negative voice.</hi> Wherefore the power in making Laws, even accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Parliaments own Declarations, cannot be taken away from the King, and he required to aſſent to all ſuch Laws as the Houſes ſhall think fit, according to the Preface of theſe new Propoſitions, without a change of the Conſtitution and fundamentall Government oſ the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Concerning the power of the Militia, Wee do deſire and ſhall be willing to agre, that it may be ſo ſetled, as neither the King nor any other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115646:11"/> be able to diſturb or infringe the peace now to be agreed upon. And wee think that in his Meſſage from <hi>Caresbrook-Caſtle</hi> he hath offered that which ſhould be very ſatisfactory; But that the King, his poſterity and the Crown ſhould for ever be diveſted of all power and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight of the Militia, is different from our judgements. For if the Crown have no power of the Militia, how can they be able to reſiſt their enemies, and the enemies of the Kingdom, protect their ſubjects, or keep freindſhip or correſpondence with their Allies? All Kings by their Royall office and Oath of Coronation are obliged to protect their Laws and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: It were ſtrange then to ſeclude the Crown for ever from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of doing, that, which by the oath of Coronation they are obliged to perform, and the obedience whereunto falleth within the oath of Allegeance. And certainly if the King and His poſterity, ſhall have no power in making Laws, nor in the Militia, it roots up the ſtrongeſt foundation of honour and ſafety which the Crown affords; and will be interpreted in the eyes of the world, to be a wreſting of the Scepter and Sword out of their hands. It is very far from our deſires that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ſhould be at the abſolute height of an Arbitrary and tyrannicall power; Neither deſire we Juſt Monarchicall power to be wronged and rendred contemptible: But to have ſuch a golden Mediocrity as they may be able to protect their ſubjects, and oppoſe their enemies according to the fundamentall Laws, and ancient conſtitution of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Before the laſt propoſitions were ſent to his Majeſty at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> both in verball debates and in our writings, wee did ſhew, That we were unſatisfied concerning ſeverall particulars contained in thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions; particularly, when we did conſent, that the power and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Militia ſhould be ſetled in the houſes of Parliament for a time, wee did it with this proviſion, that it were underſtood to be without prejudice to the right and intereſt of the Crown; And that the King and His poſterity be not totally excluded and rendred incapable to protect their ſubjects, and oppoſe the enemies of the Kingdoms: And farther when wee gave way to the ſending of thoſe Propoſitions, wee did declare it to be our judgement, that divers things craved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, were ſuch, as peace or warre ought not to depend upon the grant or refuſall of them; We ever did and muſt ſtill hold it as a good rule in the making of a peace, that the more moderate and reaſonable our de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, wee may expect the firmer peace. Wherefore as in the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115646:11"/> betwixt the King and the Parliament, wee think it very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to exclude the King from his Juſt power in the Militia; ſo when we look upon the Liberty of the ſubject, we think neither King nor Parliament ought to keep up an Army in the field, when the warre is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to the vaſte expence and utter impoveriſhing of the people; the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Bands of the Kingdom, (which may be made uſe of with litttle charge) and the forces which may be kept in ſome chief Garriſons, being ſufficient to ſuppreſſe any commotion or diſturbance that is likely to ariſe upon occaſion of the late troubles. And we conceive an Army ſhould be kept up only in the caſe of a powerfull Inſurrection within the Kingdom, or of a forraign invaſion from without, and otherwiſe to maintain a perpetuall Army in the bowels of the Kingdom upon the expence of the ſubject, when there is no enemy to fight with, is but to enſlave the King and Kingdome under a Military bondage.</p>
               <p>When our Army returned to Scotland, it was confidently expected that the Houſes ſhould have ſpeedily disbanded their Army, (the warre being at an end and no viſible enemy in the Kingdom) and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſetling of a peace here, and to the effectuall relief of Ireland: But now after a full years delay almoſt, we do not finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all theſe propoſitions, any thing concerning the disbanding of Armies, or ſending releif to that diſtreſſed Kingdom; but on the contrary there is only proviſion made for keeping up armies, and raiſing money for their maintenance. Wee muſt therefore declare to the Houſes, that it is our judgment and earneſt deſire, that there may be a Propoſition for disbanding Armies in both Kingdome. Armies were raiſed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Religion, the Kings perſon and authority, the Priviledges of Parliament, and the liberty of the ſubject. And when they are no more uſefull for theſe ends, and the Houſes may conſult freely and act ſecurely without any hoſtile oppoſition, It is high time to disband them, that the Laws of the Kingdom may take place. Some of out neighbour nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are neceſſitated to keep up Armies becauſe they have enemies, that lie contiguous and adjoyning to their borders; but the ſea is our Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark. And if wee ſtudy amity and peace amongſt our ſelves, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the union between the Kingdoms under his Majeſties government, wee need not fear forrain invaſion. It is a Cuſtome in other Nations to keep up Armies, to levy monies by force; But theſe are free King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; and when they have been fighting for liberty and freedom, wee truſt, that it is not intended that warre ſhould be made a trade, or that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115646:12"/> their warrs ſhall end in ſlavery. The continuance of Armies will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly increaſe factions and diviſions, to the great weakning of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, &amp; will in end expoſe us as a prey to our enemies; neither is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſo long as they are kept up, that there can be a ſetled <hi>peace.</hi> The charge of entertaining Armies is needleſſe, when there is no enemy, and extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grievous to the people, who before were willing to bear it, when they ſaw a neceſſity for it. And now after ſo great ſufferings and vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Treaſure to ſouldiers for many years together, the burthen is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſupportable. For theſe and many other reaſons which wee could adde, wee hold it moſt neceſſary, That as there is a Propoſition for payment of the arreares of the Army; ſo alſo there be an additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto it for their disbanding.</p>
               <p>Touching the conferring titles of honor, we deſire the King who is the fountain of honor, may not be deprived of that which in all ages and Kingdoms, hath been held and eſteemed a flowre of the Crown, and wherewith Kings doe uſually recompence the vertue and merites of ſuch as doe memorable ſervices to the Crown or Kingdome. And as to the diſpoſing of the great offices of State, and nameing of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Counſellors, we conceive his Majeſties offer, in his late Meſſage of the ſixteenth of November, to be ſo reaſonable, as may give ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Houſes.</p>
               <p>That which we are to ſpeak of next in order, is, the union and joynt intereſt of the Kingdoms, where we wiſh we had not juſt cauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate, that the Houſes have omitted the Covenant in theſe Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; rejected all that concerns Vnity and Vniformity in Religion; and have altered the former <hi>Propoſition</hi> for confirmation of the Treaties, and deſired now only an Approbation of the making of them, which amounts to no more then an Act of indemnity. They have alſo in that Propoſition omitted theſe words <hi>With all other ordinances and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings paſt betwixt the two Kingdoms, and whereunto they are obliged by the foreſaid Treaties;</hi> which words were inſerted in the former propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, after ſerious debate; and therefore if the Houſes intend to make good, and perform all ordinances paſt betwixt the Kingdoms, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their manifold profeſſions; We deſire that this Propoſition may remain as before without any alteration or omiſſion. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition deſiring his Majeſties conſent to what the two Kindoms ſhall agree upon, in purſuance of the Articles of the large treaty, which are not yet finiſhed, is omitted. The joynt declaration of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115646:12"/> is likewiſe omitted; And generally throughout theſe Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons all expreſſions of joynt intereſt are left out. And whereas former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Propoſitions of both Kingdoms were drawn up together in one body: now for ſeparating the intereſt of the Kingdoms, the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions for England, are drawn up apart; which new way, when we did obſerve, and what eſſentiall alterations, omiſſions, and additions were made in the matter of the Propoſitions, we deſired a conference for removing all differences, and that we might the more ſpeedily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to an agreement; but it was not granted: however we have herein diſcharged our duty, that we uſe all means to prevent difference, and that we for our part, ſtudy to obſerve the Treaty betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Where it is expreſly provided in the eighth Article, <hi>That no Ceſſation nor any pacification or agreement for peace whatſoever, ſhall be made by either Kingdom, or the Armies of either Kingdom, without the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall advice and conſent of both Kingdoms, or their Committees in that behalf appointed;</hi> and here we think it not amiſſe to remember the Houſes of Parliament of their expreſſions in a declaration to the Lords States Generall of the united Provinces of the Low-Countries, ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing why they did not admit of the mediation of the Dutch Ambaſſadors between the King and Parliament in the way and manner it was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, without application to the Kingdome of Scotland. The words of the declaration are, <hi>that both the Kingdoms are mutually engaged in the Propoſitions and Treaty thereupon; And that neither could admit of their Mediation without conſent of the other, becauſe the two Kingdoms were united by ſolemn League and Covenant made to Almighty God, and by league each to other as one entire body to proſecute this cauſe; And that in purſuance thereof, Propoſitions for a ſafe and well grounded peace, were then preparing in a joynt way, by the Parliaments of both Kingdoms.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Lords Ambaſſadours had propounded and offered from the King, the calling of a National Synode, to correct and redreſſe the government of the Church by Biſhops; One of the Anſwers which was given thereunto in the ſaid declaration, was, <hi>That not only the Kingdom of Scotland and the Members of both Houſes of Parliament, but alſo many thouſands of others of his Majeſties ſubjects of England and Ireland, ſtand bound by their late Nationall Covenant, to endeavour the extirpation of the Church Government by Biſhops, intended in the paper of the Dutch Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, both in England and Ireland, and to hinder the ſetting of it up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in the Kingdom of Scotland.</hi> All which being duly conſidered, we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115646:13"/> are extreamly ſory, that the Houſes of Parliament, ſhould not only have given way, but countenanced the Army in their medling with the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the peace of the Kingdom, &amp; authorized Commiſſioners to treat with them, upon Propoſitions of peace (which we take to be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that theſe Propoſitions are in ſo many things agreeable to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals of the Army, eſpecially in matters of Religion,) and without all queſtion, it had been more agreeable to the Treaty betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and to former profeſſions and proceedings, that the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of peace had been framed and agreed upon, with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both Kingdoms. We have known the Houſes of Parliament formerly look upon it as an offence of a high nature for any other then themſelves to meddle in the matters of peace, eſpecially the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and officers of the Army (though in prime place and of great and eminent fidelity) making it only proper for them to be exerciſed in matters of warre, according as they ſhould receive direction from the Houſes. And much more would the Houſes have been offended, if any officers of their Army ſhould have taken upon them to offer propoſals to the King, for ſetling a peace, without authority from the houſes, as we are informed ſome officers of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Army have done. If the Houſes of Parliament had according to our earneſt deſire the third of <hi>March</hi> 1644. when they modelled their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, made choice of ſuch officers, as were known to be zealous of the Reformation of Religion, &amp; of that uniformity which both Kingdoms are obliged to promote and maintain, and if they had alſo renewed their Declaration made the twentieth of <hi>September</hi> 1643. That they could not confide in ſuch perſons to have or execute place and authority in the Armies raiſed by them, who did not approve and conſent to the Covenant; or if their Ordnance on the 15 of <hi>February</hi> 1644 (which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth all officers to be imployed in Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfaxes</hi> Army to take the National league &amp; Covenant of both Kingdoms, within 20 days after they were approved by the Houſes) had been really put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are very confident it would have prevented a world of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences and evils which have enſued upon the neglect thereof. Wee ſhall not further inſiſt on this ſubject, neither ſhall we inlarge our ſelves upon the proceedings of the Army; But we muſt alwayes put the Houſes of Parliament in minde, that our greateſt ſtrength is in a good agreement with the King, and a firme Union between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115646:13"/>
               <p>There is left out in theſe Propoſitions, the Propoſition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the City of <hi>London,</hi> whereby they were to have the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their owne Militia and the Tower, and aſſurance that their Forces ſhall not be compelled to goe out of the City for Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Service, without their owne conſent. An Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment confirming their Charters, Cuſtomes, Liberties, &amp;c. And an Act that all the By-Laws, and Ordinances of Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell made, or to be made, ſhould bee as effectuall to all in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> and purpoſes, as if they were enacted by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with liberty alſo for them to repeale theſe Ordinaunces as they ſhall ſee cauſe. Theſe things were formerly deſired in the Propoſitions in behalfe of the City, becauſe of their affection, forwardneſſe, faithfullneſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the common cauſe of both Kingdomes. And we conceive our ſelves in duty obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to deſire that this Propoſition may not be omitted, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to His Majeſty for His aſſent.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Propoſitions for taking away the Court of Wards, and Porreſt Lands from His Majeſty, It cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when the Houſes of Parliament ſhal take into their conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, the glory and greatneſſe wherein their Kings have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that they will ever take away or diminiſh any part of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Revenue, which is neceſſary for ſupporting the Dignity of their Royall place, without giving a full recompence for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame.</p>
               <p>Touching the Propoſition for ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and diſpoſall of the Lands of Deanes and Chapters, &amp;c. as the Houſes ſhall think fit: We have onely this to ſay, that we have alwayes he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd thoſe lands were reſerved by the Houſes for maintenance of the Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie; and if they ſhould be otherwiſe diſpoſed of, it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a great diſcouragement to faithfull Paſtors, make their ſubſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> to depend upon the benevolence and charity of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and give occaſion to the people (where Miniſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wanting for lacke of maintenance) to follow after Sectaries and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Preachers.</p>
               <p>We deſire to ſee the Ordinances for Indemnity mentioned in the Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>And now to conclude, we ſhall here ſet downe moſt of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: Which are,</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115646:14"/>
               <p>That there may be a Perſonall Treaty with His Majeſty at <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Preface may be the ſame as in the former Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>That the Honourable Houſes, according to the ſolemne Vowes, Treaties, Declarations, and Engagements between the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, would after ſo very long delay, eſtabliſh the Solemne League and Covenant; and that His Majeſty be deſired to give His Royall Aſſent, for confirming the ſame by Act of Parliament in both Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>That the ſetling Reformation of, and Vniformity in Religion, according to the Covenant, in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> be likewiſe deſired in theſe new Propoſitions; And in particular, that the Confeſſion of Faith, Directory of Worſhip, Forme of Church-Government, and Catechiſing, agreed upon by the Aſſembly of Divines, and preſented to the Houſes, be eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>That by Act of Parliament, effectuall Courſe be taken for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Blaſphemy, Hereſie, Schiſme, and all ſuch ſcandalous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practiſes, as are contrary to the light of Nature, or to the knowne principles of Chriſtianity (whether concerning Faith, Worſhip, or Converſation) or to the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; or which may be deſtructive to Order and Government, or to the Peace of the Church or Kingdome.</p>
               <p>That the Ordinances concerning the calling and ſitting of the Aſſembly of Divines, be deſired to be confirmed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in the former Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>That the Propoſition for confirmation of the Treaties betwixt the Kingdomes; And all Ordinances and proceedings betwixt them be expreſſed as in the former Propoſitions. And that the Treaty for the returne of the Scots Army, of the Date of the 23 of Decemb. 1646. be inſerted amongſt the reſt.</p>
               <p>That His Majeſties Aſſent be deſired to what the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſhall agree upon, in proſecution of the Articles of the large Treaty, which are not yet finiſhed: And that all other things concerning joynt-Intereſt, or the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, which are omitted, be inſerted, and expreſſed as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>That Armies in both Kingdomes, which were raiſed for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115646:14"/> and Reformation of Religion, And for defence of the Kings Perſon, and ſafety of the Kingdomes, be not kept up to hinder Reformation of Religion, And the King from His Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, And to be a burthen to the Subjects, ſince the Warre is ended; but that they may have due ſatisfaction of their Arreares, and be disbanded; without which, there can be no reall nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Peace; That all Armies being disbanded here, ſpeedy reliefe may be ſent to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That an Act of Oblivion, which is the bond of Peace, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, to be paſt in the Parliaments of both Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>That the King be reſtored to his Rights and Revenues, and particularly that the Crowne be not excluded from the power of making Lawes, which is as eſſentiall to Kings, as to governe by Lawes, and ſway the Scepter; Nor from the power of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> without which they can neither protect their Subjects, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their and the Kingdomes enemies, nor keep friendſhip with their Allyes.</p>
               <p>That there be a concluſion added to the Propoſitions, promiſing our reall endeavours (as was done in the Propoſitions Treated upon at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi>) that his Majeſty may live in the ſplendor and glory of his Royall Progenitors, as beſeemeth His Royall place and Dignity; That ſo all differences and troubles may end in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall confidence and rejoycing; the King may enjoy the comfort of His Royall Conſort and Children, with other contentments; And wee, after ſo great diſtractions, and long continued ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, may reap the bleſſed fruits of Truth and Peace under his Government.</p>
               <p>And as it is very far from our thoughts and intentions in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing our Differences upon the Propoſitions, to provoke or give offence; ſo we truſt, that our freedome in diſcharge of the truſt committed to us, proceeding from our zeale to Religion, Loyalty to the King, and love to Peace; ſhall receive a co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Interpretation from the Honourable Houſes. And that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their wiſedome, not ſlight the deſires of a Kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the time of <hi>Englands</hi> greateſt danger, eſteemed no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> too hard for their Aſſiſtance; And are now ſeeking nothing, but the performance of the mutuall Obligements, Declarations, and Treaties betweene the two Kingdomes, And to prevent the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115646:15"/> which may cauſe upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſolemne engagements.</p>
               <p>The Houſes of Parliament have frequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntly profeſſed, that the chiefe end of their Warres was the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Religion according to the Covenant. And they have often Promiſed and Declared to the King and to all the World, (n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Name of God) that no trouble or ſucceſſe ſhould ever make them wrong or diminiſh the power of the Crowne, which were the chiefe mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es and Arguments that indured <hi>Scotland</hi> to engage with them in this Warre. Let therefore that be given to God which is Gods, and to <hi>Caeſar</hi> what is <hi>Caeſars;</hi> whereby it may be evident that you are not unmindfull of the ſolemne Vowes you made to God in the time of diſtreſſe, for Reformation of Religion; and it may alſo really appeare, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> advantages and power which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> put into your hands, hath not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your Loyalty to the King. And according to our many profeſſions, and neare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ally and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ly, che<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh and ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng then the V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion between the two Kingdomes under his Majeſty, by all the Pledges of reciprocall kindneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo Religion and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may flouriſh, and both Kingdomes, languiſhing under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of an naturall Warre, may live in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nty.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By Command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. IO. CHEIS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <p>WEE <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions communica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherein the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the King, care <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Parliament <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Parliament to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to bee made;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115646:15"/> and a new Propoſition for the adjournments of both Houſes. To which Bills they are commanded to deſire His Majeſties aſſent by His Letters Patents under the great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. And after His Majeſties aſſent to thoſe Bils, the Houſes of Parliament will ſend a Committee of both Houſes to Treate with His Majeſty in the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> upon the remainder of the new Propoſitions. To all which wee anſwer; That, although there be nothing which we more paſſionately deſire then a happy Peace, and good agreement with the King; yet we cannot agree to this way of deſiring His Majeſtyes aſſent to thoſe four Bills, before any Treaty with His Majeſty upon other Propoſitions, it being in our judgment neither for the good of Religion, the King nor Kingdomes. And firſt concerning Religion, we ſay, that in <hi>January,</hi> 1645. it was agreed on betwixt the Houſes of Parliament and us, before the Treaty at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge; That the Propoſitions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion the Militia, and Ireland, ſhall bee treated upon</hi> alte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s vicibus, <hi>beginning firſt with the Propoſition of Religion, and that as it is of moſt excellency, ſo it is to bee ſought after and finally agreed upon in the fi ſt place before any finall agreement the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> upon any of the other Propoſitions.</hi> Wee are very ſure the Houſes had far greater reaſon at that time, to looke to their ſecurity, and to deſire the Propoſition for ſetling the Militia to be firſt agreed on, when the King had an Army in the field, then now when they have a ſtrong Army, and he has none at all. And upon the other part the danger to Religion is now much greater them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any time before when men in Armes are demanding a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of all ſorts of Religions (Popery excepted.) And if firſt of all it ſhould be agreed on, that the continuance of ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſhall be ſetled by Law, wee deſire it may be equally conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, what good can be expected from a treaty upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or what hopes ſhall remaine of ſetling it according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; wherefore we cannot conſent to the ſending any Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rity for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ling Peace without T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, which hath been acknowledged both by His Majeſty, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all former Treaties or Meſſages, to bee the beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> foundation of a laſting Peace. And we muſt ſtill preſſe that there may be a preference of thoſe deſires which are for ſetling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the Goverment of the Church: the want <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Sects and Hereſies which doe multiply and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115646:16"/> daily, to the diſturbance of all Order and Peace, both in Church and State.</p>
               <p>As this way is not for the good of Religion, ſo it cannot in reaſon be conceived, that it ſhall bee acceptable to the King; for how can it bee expected that he will grant thoſe things for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Treaty (whereof the iſſue is uncertain) which he hath ever hitherto denyed even to obtaine a Peace (eſpecially when after all his Majeſties earneſt deſires, hee cannot bee admitted to come to <hi>London,</hi> nor upon any tearms to have a Treaty here, in reſpect the Houſes conceive that the Kings preſence with them, at this time ſtands not with the ſafety and ſecurity of the Parliament and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but that the Kings aſſent to the four Bills muſt be by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and thereafter a Treaty upon the reſt of the Propoſitions at the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> (Or, can it be looked for, that Hee will give the whole and ſole power of the Militia from himſelfe and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, to the Houſes for their ſecurity, and to bee diſpoſed of as they ſhall think fit, and have no ſecurity at all to himſelfe, nor any aſſurrance that he ſhall be reſtored to his Rights and Government? It is much more probable, that he will thinke he hath already of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſufficient ſecurity in his late Meſſage from <hi>Carisbrooke</hi> Caſtle of the 16. <hi>Novemb.</hi> wherein he is content that all power of the Militia bee ſetled in the Houſes of Parliament during his Raigne.</p>
               <p>Neither is this way in our apprehenſions for the good and ſafety of the Kingdomes, that an Army holding ſuch principles as they do concerning Religion, and in relation to the ſetling the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Peace of the Kingdomes, and which (without any known authority from the Parliament) hath increaſed their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to neere the double of what they are allowed by order of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, (and in their late Repreſentation, acknowledge their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per numeraries to be about twenty thouſand.) That ſuch an Army (we ſay) ſhall be perpetually eſtabliſhed when there are no forces to oppoſe the Parliament, and that the ſubjects ſhall bee obliged by a Law for ever to ſubmit to a Military power, and pay what moneye ſhall be demanded for their maintenance; whatſoever it may ſeeme to others to bee, in our ſence it doth neither agree with the rules of Policy nor Safety.</p>
               <p>We did deſire to ſee the foure Bills to be preſented to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty (ſo much the rather, that from the Title of the Bill for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115646:16"/> Militia; we perceive that it doth extend to the ſetling and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of forces in the Town of <hi>Barwicke,</hi> contrary to the large Treaty betwixt the kingdomes.) And we did repreſent that thoſe Bills being aſſented unto by the King would bee a reall ſecurity, and the making an Agreement for Peace, which according to the Treaty betwixt the Kingdomes cannot be done without the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall advice and conſent of both. To which the Houſes did yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day returne as their Anſwer, <hi>That the Priviledges, Right and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Kingdome and Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>is, that Bils paſt both Houſes to bee preſented to the King for His Royall aſſent, are not to bee communicated to any other whoſoever either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Matter or Forme, before His Anſwer thereunto given. And that there is nothing contained in any Article of Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Kingdomes to the contrary.</hi> Whereunto we make this Reply, that the Bills mentioned in the 11. <hi>Sect.</hi> of the Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Peace, preſented to His Majeſty at <hi>Oxford</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1644. were communicated unto us, before they were ſent to the King, and upon peruſall of them, we did deſire that nothing might be in thoſe Bils contrary to the Covenant, or the Reformation, &amp; Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to be ſetled. Vpon conſideration wherof, the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons gave us this anſwer: That the Reformation &amp; Vniformity deſir'd, is alredy provided for, in one of the Propoſitions, to which nothing containd in thoſe Bils could be any prejudice, but ſhould hereafter bee regulated as the ſaid Reformation and Vniformity ſhall be thought fit to be ſetled. Alſo the Bil for aboliſhing Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy was communicated unto us, and afterward debated upon by his Majeſties Commiſſioners, and the Commiſſioners of both Kingdomes at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge.</hi> Wee thought fit to give theſe inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; to ſhew, that it hath not alwayes been the cuſtome of both Houſes not to communicate their Bills before His Majeſties Anſwer were given thereunto. Yet it is no wayes our deſire to meddle with the framing of your Lawes, or adviſing the forme of your Bils, we ſhall ever be tender of any juſt priviledge of Parliament; but that it ſhould be ſaid that there is nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in any Article of Treaty between the two Kingdoms, which requires the communication of the matter of any Bils, is to us very ſtrange. It is agreed upon betwixt the Kingdomes, that no Ceſſation, nor any Pacification, or Agreement for Peace whatſoever, ſhall be made by either Kingdome, or the Armies of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115646:17"/> either Kingdome, without the mutuall advice and conſent of both Kingdomes: Suppoſe the Houſes of Parliament ſhould turne all their deſires for peace into Bils, and ſhould ſay, that thoſe Bils cannot be communicated to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in relation to matter or forme: Wee deſire to know, and let any rationall man judge, whether this were not an eluding and cleare violation of the Treaty: Neither can it in this caſe be a ſatisfactory Anſwer, that the Houſes of Parliament doe only ſend four of the Propoſitions in Bils to His Majeſty; for every one of the Propoſitions is a Propoſition for peace, and an Agreement made upon any one of them is an agreement for peace. And which is much more, there are none of the Propoſitions which in their owne nature doe ſo immediatly concerne the ſetling of a peace, as theſe foure Propoſitions; and what can be called an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement for peace if this bee not? when the King by His aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhall juſtifie the proceedings of the Parliament in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te warre, and make all Oaths, Declarations, Proclamations, and other proceedings againſt it to be void, when by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſhall ſettle the power of all Forces by Sea and Land into the Houſes of Parliament, and alſo to raiſe monies for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: when he ſhall conſent that all Peers made, or hereafter to be made, ſhall not ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or vote in Parliament without conſerre of both Houſes, and when hee ſhall give power to the Houſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe at their pleaſure: If then, the Kings aſſent to thoſe Bils be an Agreement for peace, (as we hope it cannot in reaſon be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd) our advice and conſent ought to be had therein, before they be ſent to the King, and otherwiſe the Treaty is violated.</p>
               <p>As we cannot agree to this way of ſending theſe foure Bills to His Majeſty for His Aſſent before any Treaty upon the reſt of the Propoſitions; ſo wee are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly unſatisfied with the matter of theſe new Propoſitions lately con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> us; for the reaſons expreſſed in our Anſwer unto them, which we doe herewith deliver unto your Lordſhips, to be preſented to both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And we doe deſire that they would take the whole buſineſſe unto their fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration, and that there may be a perſonall Treaty with His Majeſty here a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon ſuch Propoſitions as ſhall be agreed upon, with advice and conſent of both Kingdomes according to the Treaty.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>By Command of the Commiſſioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. IO. CHEIS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Decemb.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
